Whey protein has, for a very long time,
been deemed the king of protein for its
absorption, its digestibility, and its
stellar amino acid profile. When you see
the gym bros shaking up their protein
shakes, the money is good that the
protein that they're shaking is whey.
However, new research out of multiple
studies indicates a new protein may be
trying to take the crown. But, here's
the thing. I'm going to introduce you to
exciting research, but within that
exciting research are some sobering
results. And, in the end, I'm going to
present you with a hypothesis that I'm
curious if you'll actually agree with
it. So, please comment below when we get
to that point. Yes, I will respond to as
many comments as I can. Okay, so is this
the new king of protein, or does whey
retain its title? Like I mentioned from
the top, whey protein is considered the
king of protein for a number of reasons,
among which is its perfect PDCAAS
which stands for protein digestibility
corrected amino acid score. Now, there
are other protein sources like eggs that
also have a perfect score, but the sheer
potency of whey and ease of consumption
makes it, to many, the king. Now, a new
kid on the block called
beta-lactoglobulin
is trying to overthrow whey. The funny
thing is that this is akin to Star Wars.
Yes, Star Wars. As Anakin
is learning from Obi-Wan Kenobi,
beta-lactoglobulin
is typically extracted from whey
protein, making it an even purer form of
the protein since whey is separated from
milk. So, it's almost like Anakin
learning all his skills from Obi-Wan
Kenobi to then betray him. But, does
beta-lactoglobulin
have enough power to overcome this
master whey? Well, one of the things
that makes whey protein so potent is its
concentration of essential amino acids,
especially the most powerful muscle
growth stimulating amino acids like
leucine. However, like Anakin wielding
the advantage of the dark side of the
force, beta-lactoglobulin contains even
more leucine, and more gets absorbed,
evidence in this study. The
beta-lactoglobulin, which, if you don't
mind, I'm going to start calling it BLG,
is blue, and the whey protein is in,
well
also blue, but lighter blue.
The line graph indicates the rise in
blood leucine over time, and the right
bar graph indicates the total amount of
leucine over the entire experimental
period. In both, you'll notice the BLG
condition has greater leucine levels.
The point here being that one of the big
advantages of whey protein is its highly
muscle growth stimulating leucine
levels. Yet, BLG, beta-lactoglobulin,
contains more and delivers more to the
bloodstream.
So, by traditional muscle physiology
thought, we might expect this new BLG
protein to lead to greater muscle growth
and possibly greater strength. Luckily,
we have a study that looked at that very
question. In this study, participants
were split between consuming a whey
protein or the BLG protein over 2 months
while also resistance training.
Their calories and their total protein
were the same. Then again, they see a
rise in blood leucine when consuming BLG
protein over the previous leucine king,
whey. And yet, when we look at the
amount of lean mass, which includes
muscle we see no differences between the
two protein conditions. In fact, when
also looking at strength, while both
proteins plus training led to big
improvements in strength, the BLG
protein was not superior to whey. In
fact, since we've been discussing
leucine and its muscle growth potential,
that's usually reflected in something
called the synthesis rate. In this first
study that we went over, the researchers
looked at synthesis rate, which is the
amount of protein produced within the
muscle cells. And, as you can see, while
yes, protein synthesis did increase with
protein consumption and exercise,
there's no difference between the two
tall bars, indicating no increased
protein synthesis. Okay, no differences
in protein synthesis, no differences in
assumed muscle growth. Technically, lean
mass is a less sensitive measure of
muscle mass directly, but still, there's
no hint of any benefit of BLG, although
it raises leucine more than whey. Like I
mentioned, some exciting data and some
sobering news as well. But, now comes my
hypothesis, which I would like your
input on, because
it could break open the importance of
BLG.
Before I get into that, and get into how
to apply this information, there's more
data on the hormonal effects of BLG, why
BLG may be especially powerful for
people with insulin resistance, and more
on the mechanisms of BLG. Covering all
that in the more involved, extended
version of this video that you're
currently watching. It's included for
the Physio Logic Insiders, my premium
research platform, and you get an
accompanying article along with all my
multiple analyses that I've released for
the Insiders. Oh, and of course, these
perks right here. Private podcast, live
sessions, private community. Need I say
more? You can join through the link in
the description. I would love for you to
join the Insiders. Okay, my hypothesis
is based on something called the leucine
threshold, which is a basement effect of
muscle protein synthesis effect of
leucine. As in you have to eat enough
leucine to stimulate protein synthesis.
Too little does not stimulate protein
synthesis, and therefore muscle growth.
In addition, there's a ceiling effect,
as in just ever increasing your leucine
intake does not yield more protein
synthesis. There is a cap. So, how does
that relate here? Well, check this study
out. Where four groups of people were
given different amounts of leucine, and
their protein synthesis was measured.
Here are the data. The higher the bars
go, the more muscle protein synthesis
has occurred. Now, the black bars are
before leucine, and white are after
leucine consumption. Then, we have two
different amounts of leucine and two
different age categories, making four
groups. Notice, crucially, how the young
individuals at both concentrations of
leucine experienced an increase in
muscle protein synthesis. However, also
notice that the older individuals did
not experience an increase in synthesis
at the lower leucine levels, and only
experienced an increase with the greater
leucine consumption. So, this speaks to
both the basement and the ceiling
effect. Now, I promise this is going to
relate relate to BLG in a minute. Hang
tight.
The young individuals are hitting the
ceiling at lower leucine consumption as
the higher leucine intake did not yield
greater muscle protein synthesis
compared to the reduced leucine
consumption. On the other hand, the
older individuals aren't hitting the
basement, the initial threshold, with
the low leucine, only with the high
leucine condition.
In simple terms
younger people are more sensitive to
leucine and require less to maximize
their muscle protein synthesis. And
older people are less sensitive, so they
require more leucine to achieve the same
muscle protein synthesis. Okay. You may
be see where I'm going with this.
Now, back to BLG. The reason this
relates is because this one study on
muscle growth only recruited young
individuals. So, yes, they had more
leucine in their blood from BLG, but if
the whey protein levels of leucine were
sufficient to maximize muscle protein
synthesis
the extra leucine may not be doing
anything. So, my hypothesis is that
there's a possibility
that if they repeated this study in
people who are in their 60s and older,
they might actually detect a difference
between BLG protein and the whey
protein, as the BLG protein is designed
more optimally for those with less
leucine sensitivity. So, they can take
advantage of the greater leucine intake.
So
let me know. What do you think? Let's
discuss. Okay, hypothesis aside for a
moment, here's how I think about BLG,
good old beta-lactoglobulin.
It's certainly enticing, the data are
exciting, but for the everyday person,
would I dethrone whey protein?
No. I think for most people looking at
highly concentrated protein sources in
supplement form, whey protein still
remains king and lord of these lands.
Then, if you're the biohacker type, and
you don't care if the limited data
indicates no difference, but you're
compelled by the extra leucine, I'd
still encourage you to stick with whey
protein. You'll be paying a pretty penny
for nothing of real value. However
if you are a person over the age of 60,
and you're looking for a slightly higher
quality protein to consume at lower
doses, there might be a use case for use
of BLG over whey. Alternatively, you
could just up your whey consumption a
bit. Also, keep in mind that's based on
speculation, not on strong data. So,
like I said, in most cases, whey protein
shall remain king, lord, and conqueror
of the protein lands. But, don't go to
the dark lands where muscles don't grow,
for that is beyond our borders. You must
never go there, Simba.
But, where I do encourage you to go next
is where the light touches in this next
video right here. I'll catch you in the
next one. Thanks for nerding out with
me. See you.